<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: architecture | Huteri Manza Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://huteri.me/blog/categories/architecture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://huteri.me/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-20T13:01:58+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://huteri.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Huteri Manza]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Mistakes When Doing Clean Architecture in Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://huteri.me/2017/08/08/things-to-note-about-clean-code-in-android/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-08T16:21:47+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://huteri.me/2017/08/08/things-to-note-about-clean-code-in-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a while. Let&rsquo;s talk about clean architecture in Android. We know that best practices for clean architecture are changing fast. Look on what Google has done with its architecture components. For more detail about architecture components, <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/architecture/index.html">click here</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>But, it&rsquo;s not what I want to talk today. Let&rsquo;s talk more about common mistakes when doing clean archictecture in Android.</p>

<h3>1. Not able to move logic from Activity/Fragment to Presenter/ViewModel</h3>

<p>I believe that view must be passive, it means that we should make it as dumb as possible, so there is no way we can have bug in a view code. Every method in a view is supposed to do exactly one thing, no more, no if.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look on a good example</p>

<pre><code class="java">
interface LoginView extends BaseView {

    void showPasswordInvalid();

    void showUsernameRequired();

    void navigateToMainPage();

    void showLoginError();

    void showLoginSucceed();

    void showInputOtpDialog();

    void showAlreadyLogin();

}
</code></pre>

<p>Basically, a method is verbose enough for us to understand so there is no room for error. but let&rsquo;s see some of the mistakes to give us a picture</p>

<pre><code class="java">
interface LoginView extends BaseView {

    void showError(Error error);

    void navigateToActivity(Activity activity)

}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, imagine the implementation, the methods have more than 1 responsibility. <code>showError(Error error)</code> method has to parse the error first, and then decide how to show the error. it&rsquo;s more than 1 responsibility.</p>

<p>Then came a question, the good example above shows us that we have to write <code>Toast.makeText</code> for every method that needs to show error message. it breaks the principle of DRY (don&rsquo;t repeat yourself), yes, and no. Yes, we will have same functionality for every method, and no, we can improve it by creating new method in the view to show toast.</p>

<p>I know it&rsquo;s lot of boilerplate, but it&rsquo;s worth it if we think about how easy it will be to create unit test with verbose methods.</p>

<h3>2. Not to Think about Unit Test</h3>

<p>Unit test is the most useful way to make our code clean. Even if we just think about it, it will improve our code a lot. One of the tip is to always think about unit test when you write code. Think about how we are going to test it later. This is the least minimum, I mean if you do TDD, then it&rsquo;s better. No need to follow this.</p>

<p>Basically, by only thinking about unit test, we will:</p>

<h4>a. not put android framework code in the presenter/viewmodel</h4>

<h4>b. not put logic in activity/fragment because we are trying to achieve 100% coverage of the logic</h4>

<h4>c. not put complex code, but instead make everything simple</h4>

<p>Let me know what you think later after you tried it.</p>

<h3>3. Not to Think About Modularity/Separation</h3>

<p>One of the thing about clean architecture is separation. Every layer of clean architecture has their own responsibility and they only know layers below them, they only want to know that they can get the data they need.</p>

<p>With this separation, we can change the inner logic inside of one the layer, and the other layer will not care as long as it can get the data. One of the useful example is local database. There are a lot of ways implementing local database in android such as Realm, Room, and Sqlite, and this thing will change to something better in the future. So if we already implemented Realm, then how would we change it to room later?</p>

<p>This is where separations looks useful. With a clear separation, we could change to room easily without too much refactoring.</p>

<p>So, always think about separation in mind, think about how we could change the library to something better in the future, think about maintainability over features.</p>

<p>If you think there is more, add in the comment section below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Easy Way to Understand MVP in Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://huteri.me/2016/03/25/the-easy-way-to-understand-mvp-in-android/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-25T15:12:18+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://huteri.me/2016/03/25/the-easy-way-to-understand-mvp-in-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I would like to talk about MVP in android. I know that there are a lot of resources recently talking about MVP in android. MVP is now considered as the best architecture available in Android Development. I tried to learn about this clean archictecture, and I admit it is quite hard to learn for newbie like me.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I hope there is a better way to understand the concept of the MVP first before we talk about the better way in implementing MVP. This is the purpose of this article. I want to give a good and easy sample how to implement MVP in the easiest way. I have read a lot of articles about MVP, and I will put them in the references later.</p>

<p>If you are also new in MVP, then I suggest to read this post first and then continue on the article I’ll give in the references.</p>

<p>So, the core purpose of MVP is to make the code testable. if you realize that there were a litle detail about how to really implement a good unit testing in Android because unit testing was really hard in Android since we depended a lot in Android framework.</p>

<p>But, today, with MVP and clean architecture, we can improve the coverage of unit testing in our code and make them testable.</p>

<p>ok, stop talking and let’s see the code. I have written a simple android app with clean architecture. It is mostly based on the reference from Google but I improve it to make it easier to understand.</p>

<p>The good thing about this sample app is that I don’t use any third party libraries, I know it is not good, but I made it just for learning purpose. I also put some common best practices if you want to use it in real development.</p>

<p>Here we go <a href="https://github.com/huteri/mvp-android">https://github.com/huteri/mvp-android</a></p>

<p>Let’s get to the explanation. The simple way to understand MVP is to think about this figure.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://fernandocejas.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/clean_architecture_mvp.png">http://fernandocejas.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/clean_architecture_mvp.png</a>"></p>

<p>Ok, maybe it’s not that useful. So the purpose of this figure is to tell you that we should not access the data layer (Model) directly from the view. We have to use the second party called presenter to coordinate the data into the view. But why? because view is heavily depended on android framework such as activity and fragment and it makes testing data layer in the view almost impossible. Data layer consists of our business logic and it should be tested properly.</p>

<p><strong>How do we make it?</strong></p>

<p>By moving all the responsibilites of the view to presenter. Now presenter is responsible for getting and managing the data. View just shows it to UI by using android framework.</p>

<p>Now, we understand the concept, but how do we implement it? If you read carefully, we have 2 process here,</p>

<ol>
<li>Delegate all the user actions from view to presenter</li>
<li>Presenter can send the data to the view and the view should show it to UI.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let’s talk about the first process, look on this sample code</p>

<pre><code class="java MainActivity.java">package me.huteri.weather.features.main;

import android.os.Bundle;
import android.support.annotation.VisibleForTesting;
import android.support.v4.widget.SwipeRefreshLayout;
import android.support.v7.widget.LinearLayoutManager;
import android.support.v7.widget.RecyclerView;
import android.view.Menu;
import android.view.MenuItem;
import android.widget.Toast;

import java.util.List;

import me.huteri.weather.R;
import me.huteri.weather.features.BaseActivity;
import me.huteri.weather.features.adapter.WeatherListAdapter;
import me.huteri.weather.model.Weather;
import me.huteri.weather.model.service.WeatherApiImpl;


public class MainActivity extends BaseActivity implements MainView, WeatherListAdapter.WeatherItemListener {

    private MainPresenterImpl mPresenter;

    private WeatherListAdapter mWeatherListAdapter;
    private SwipeRefreshLayout mSrl;

    @Override
    protected void onCreate(Bundle savedInstanceState) {
        super.onCreate(savedInstanceState);
        setContentView(R.layout.activity_main);

        mPresenter = new MainPresenterImpl(this, new WeatherApiImpl());

        initRecyclerView();
        initSwipeRefreshLayout();
    }

    @Override
    protected void onResume() {
        super.onResume();
        mPresenter.loadWeatherData();

    }

    @Override
    public boolean onCreateOptionsMenu(Menu menu) {
        getMenuInflater().inflate(R.menu.menu_main, menu);
        return true;
    }

    @Override
    public boolean onOptionsItemSelected(MenuItem item) {
        switch (item.getItemId()) {
            case R.id.action_refresh:
                mPresenter.loadWeatherData();
                break;
        }
        return true;
    }

    @Override
    public void showProgress() {
        if(!mSrl.isRefreshing()) {

            // make sure setRefreshing() is called after the layout done everything else
            mSrl.post(new Runnable() {
                @Override
                public void run() {
                    mSrl.setRefreshing(true);
                }
            });
        }
    }

    @Override
    public void hideProgress() {
        if(mSrl.isRefreshing()) {
            mSrl.setRefreshing(false);
        }
    }

    @Override
    public void showWeatherClickedMessage(Weather s) {
        Toast.makeText(this, String.format(getString(R.string.main_toast_weather_item_click), s.getCityName()), Toast.LENGTH_SHORT).show();
    }

    @Override
    public void showWeathers(List&lt;Weather&gt; weathers) {
        mWeatherListAdapter.replaceData(weathers);

    }

    @Override
    public void showConnectionError() {
        Toast.makeText(this, R.string.main_error_connection, Toast.LENGTH_SHORT).show();
    }

    @Override
    public void onWeatherItemClick(Weather item) {
        mPresenter.clickWeatherItem(item);

    }

    private void initSwipeRefreshLayout() {

        mSrl = (SwipeRefreshLayout) findViewById(R.id.srl);
        mSrl.setOnRefreshListener(new SwipeRefreshLayout.OnRefreshListener() {
            @Override
            public void onRefresh() {
                mPresenter.loadWeatherData();
            }
        });

    }

    private void initRecyclerView() {
        mWeatherListAdapter = new WeatherListAdapter(this, this);

        RecyclerView rvWeatherList = (RecyclerView) findViewById(R.id.rv_main);
        rvWeatherList.setLayoutManager(new LinearLayoutManager(this));
        rvWeatherList.setAdapter(mWeatherListAdapter);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>See, I just delegate methods to presenter with <code>mPresener.theMethodHere()</code>. Just ignore code you don’t know, we’ll talk about that later. Now look on the presenter.</p>

<pre><code class="java MainPresenter.java">package me.huteri.weather.features.main;

import me.huteri.weather.model.Weather;

public interface MainPresenter{
    void loadWeatherData();
    void clickWeatherItem(Weather item);
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="java MainPresenterImpl.java">package me.huteri.weather.features.main;


import java.util.List;

import me.huteri.weather.features.BasePresenter;
import me.huteri.weather.model.Weather;
import me.huteri.weather.model.service.WeatherApi;
import me.huteri.weather.model.service.WeatherApiImpl;
import me.huteri.weather.util.EspressoIdlingResource;

/**
 * The implementation of the main presenter interface
 */

public class MainPresenterImpl extends BasePresenter implements MainPresenter {

    private final MainView mView;
    private final WeatherApiImpl mWeatherApi;

    public MainPresenterImpl(MainView view, WeatherApiImpl weatherApi) {
        mView = view;
        mWeatherApi = weatherApi;
    }

    @Override
    public void loadWeatherData() {

        mView.showProgress();

        EspressoIdlingResource.increment();

        mWeatherApi.getAllWeathers(new WeatherApi.WeatherServiceCallback&lt;List&lt;Weather&gt;&gt;() {

            @Override
            public void onSuccess(List&lt;Weather&gt; weathers) {
                EspressoIdlingResource.decrement();
                mView.hideProgress();
                mView.showWeathers(weathers);
            }

            @Override
            public void onFailure() {
                EspressoIdlingResource.decrement();
                mView.showConnectionError();
                mView.hideProgress();
            }
        });
    }

    @Override
    public void clickWeatherItem(Weather item) {
        mView.showWeatherClickedMessage(item);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>In the presenter, we define the method for <code>MainPresenter.theMethodHere()</code>, basically all the methods delegated from view. It’s that simple. Now let’s talk about the second process, presenter should send the data to view, and the view should show it to UI. If you are looking carefully in the presenter, we have <code>MainView</code> interface. It’s for the second process, the way for presenter to send the data to view, and the view should show it to UI.</p>

<pre><code class="java MainView.java">package me.huteri.weather.features.main;

import java.util.List;

import me.huteri.weather.model.Weather;

public interface MainView {
    void showProgress();
    void hideProgress();
    void showWeatherClickedMessage(Weather s);
    void showWeathers(List&lt;Weather&gt; weathers);
    void showConnectionError();
}
</code></pre>

<p>And <code>MainActivity</code> only needs to implement this interface. We implement MainView interface because this is the way for the presenter to inform the view.</p>

<p>Basically, MVP is just like that but we are just talking about view layer here, we are not talking about data layer.</p>

<p>With this principle, we can test our data layer usage in presenter easily.</p>

<pre><code class="java MainPresenterImplTest.java">package me.huteri.weather.features.main;

import org.junit.Before;
import org.junit.Test;
import org.mockito.ArgumentCaptor;
import org.mockito.Captor;
import org.mockito.Mock;
import org.mockito.MockitoAnnotations;

import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.List;

import me.huteri.weather.model.Weather;
import me.huteri.weather.model.service.WeatherApi;
import me.huteri.weather.model.service.WeatherApiImpl;

import static org.mockito.Mockito.verify;

public class MainPresenterImplTest {

    @Mock
    private MainView mMainView;

    @Mock
    private WeatherApiImpl mWeatherApi;

    /**
     * {@link ArgumentCaptor} is a powerful Mockito API to capture callback from background task and then perform assertion
     */
    @Captor
    private ArgumentCaptor&lt;WeatherApi.WeatherServiceCallback&gt; mWeatherServiceCallback;

    private MainPresenterImpl mMainPresenter;

    @Before
    public void setupMainPresenter() {
        MockitoAnnotations.initMocks(this);

        mMainPresenter = new MainPresenterImpl(mMainView, mWeatherApi);
    }

    @Test
    public void testLoadWeatherData_andSucceed() throws Exception {

        List&lt;Weather&gt; sample = generateSampleWeatherList();

        mMainPresenter.loadWeatherData();
        verify(mMainView).showProgress();
        verify(mWeatherApi).getAllWeathers(mWeatherServiceCallback.capture());

        mWeatherServiceCallback.getValue().onSuccess(sample);

        verify(mMainView).hideProgress();
        verify(mMainView).showWeathers(sample);

    }

    @Test
    public void testLoadWeatherData_andFailed() throws Exception {
        mMainPresenter.loadWeatherData();
        verify(mMainView).showProgress();

        verify(mWeatherApi).getAllWeathers(mWeatherServiceCallback.capture());
        mWeatherServiceCallback.getValue().onFailure();

        verify(mMainView).hideProgress();
        verify(mMainView).showConnectionError();
    }

    @Test
    public void testClickWeatherItem_showsWeatherMessage() throws Exception {
        Weather item = new Weather(22.1f, 3, "Jakarta", "Sample Description");

        mMainPresenter.clickWeatherItem(item);
        verify(mMainView).showWeatherClickedMessage(item);
    }

    private List&lt;Weather&gt; generateSampleWeatherList() {
        Weather item1 = new Weather(22.4f, 3, "Jakarta", "Cloudy");
        Weather item2 = new Weather(30.4f, 3, "Singapore", "Raining");

        List&lt;Weather&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;();
        list.add(item1);
        list.add(item2);

        return list;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The test uses mockito to mock some dependency such as MainView interface and the data layer. After understanding the basic of this simple MVP, continue on reading the article in references. It will give you a little bit more undestanding about MVP.</p>

<p>The full source code is available on <a href="https://github.com/huteri/mvp-android">github</a></p>

<p><strong>References</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://codelabs.developers.google.com/codelabs/android-testing/index.html">https://codelabs.developers.google.com/codelabs/android-testing/index.html</a></p>

<p><a href="http://fernandocejas.com/2014/09/03/architecting-android-the-clean-way/">http://fernandocejas.com/2014/09/03/architecting-android-the-clean-way/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4L7G1uaQ67s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4L7G1uaQ67s</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.thedroidsonroids.com/blog/android/example-realm-mvp-dagger/">http://www.thedroidsonroids.com/blog/android/example-realm-mvp-dagger/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
